Inventory of the Addison A. Spaugh Papers, 1876-1979
University of Wyoming. American Heritage Center.
Addison A. Spaugh papers
1876-1979
Spaugh, Addison A. (Addison Augustus), 1857-1943
00293
1 cubic ft. (1 slim document box + 1 F24 oversize box)
University of Wyoming. American Heritage Center.
The collection contains a small amount of correspondence, photographs, and other papers including newspaper and magazine articles by or about Addison A. Spaugh, a Wyoming rancher and businessman.
Biography of Addison A. Spaugh
Addison A. Spaugh was a Wyoming rancher and businessman. He was born in Indiana in 1857 and arrived in Wyoming with a trail herd of Texas cattle in 1874. From 1879 he was employed by Manville & Peck, founders of the OW brand on Hat Creek. He became foreman of the Converse Cattle Company in 1880; and in 1885 he began ranching on his own near the town of Manville (which he named), expanding rapidly by buying ranches and brands both north and south of Manville. He acquired the 77 and the Horseshoe ranches from T.B. Hord about 1897. In 1910 he began to divest himself of range interests and by 1917 had turned to banking in an effort to build up the town of Keeline, which he had platted. He held interests in banks in Glenrock, Cheyenne, and Douglas, but sold them as a result of pressures in World War I. In 1913 Spaugh and H.B. Card acquired the Jireh Record, which they published for a time together with the Keeline Courier. Spaugh was also interested in the development of the Lance Creek oil field. In 1929, however, Spaugh declared bankruptcy. In 1941 he retired altogether from management of his remaining ranch interests. He first married Estella R. Bailey. His second wife, Marguerite, who survived him, later married A.G. Underwood. Addison A. Spaugh died in Denver in 1943 and was buried in Manville, Wyoming.
Scope and Content
The collection contains a small amount of correspondence and other papers; photocopies of a legal document regarding sale of some land in New York in 1887; a narrative by Spaugh about his discovery of the Spanish Diggings (an ancient Native American quarry site); and photographs of Spaugh (1890-1940 and undated), the OW Ranch and employees (circa 1880s), cattle, and Manville, Wyoming (1907). The oversize box contains magazines and newspapers with articles by or about A.A. Spaugh.
Access Restrictions
There are no access restrictions on the materials for research purposes, and the collection is open to the public.
Related Materials
There is another known archival collection created by Addison A. Spaugh at the date of processing. See:
Addison A. Spaugh collection, 1889-1941, DCLV99-A188, Wyoming State Archives (Cheyenne, Wyo.).
Acquisition Information
The collection was received from Marguerite Spaugh Underwood in 1957. The photocopies from New York were received with a letter about the first Mrs. Spaugh from Alderman Gleason in 1979. Another accretion was purchased in 1977.
Access Terms
Ranching--Wyoming.; Archaeology--Wyoming.; Indians--North America--Wyoming.;; Wyoming--History--to 1889.; Wyoming--History--1890-1918.; Wyoming--History--1919-1945.; Photographs.
Agriculture and Natural Resources; Ranching; Business, Industry, Labor, and Commerce; Businesses and Corporations; Wyoming
Container List
- Papers – Biographical Material, 1898-1936 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Newspaper clippings; brand cards
- Papers – Correspondence, 1885-1957 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Papers – Correspondence: Barrow, M. C. (Bill Barlow), 1898-1907 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Papers – Correspondence and Deed, 1887, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  (Photocopy); A.F. Gleason donation regarding Estelle Bailey Spaugh
- Papers – “Discovery of the Spanish Diggings,”, 1925, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  Typescript and letter by Addison A. Spaugh
- Papers – Reprints: “Famous OW Roundup of 1884,” etc., 1926, 1934 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Photographs – Cattle, 1893, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Photographs – Great Western Mining Co., Silver Cliff, Wyo., 1885 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Photographs – Horseshoe Ranch, 1895 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Photographs – Manville, Wyoming, 1907 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Photographs – OW Ranch, 1885, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Photographs – OW Ranch: Employees, circa 1883, 1904 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  (Identified); Jack Blackwell; Sid Brace; H.B. Card; Hank Green; Otis Hughes; Wesley Wolf; others
- Photographs – Spaugh, Addison A., 1876-1940 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Photographs – Miscellaneous, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Magazines – Country Gentleman, November 1939- March 1940 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  Contains “The Last Frontier,” by Frazier Hunt
- Newspapers – Bill Barlow’s Budget, 1898, 1914 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  Contains articles about A.A. Spaugh
- Newspapers – Jireh Record, November 22, 1913, November 29, 1913 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  Edited by A.A. Spaugh
- Newspapers – Keeline Courier, 1913-1914 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Newspapers – Lusk Free Lance, Lusk Herald, May 17, 1934, May 28, 1936 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Newspapers – Manville News (extra), May 22, 1919 (Box 2, Folder 6)